foreign
[Music]
hello and welcome this is active live
stream number 50.2 it's November 3rd
2022 and it's our third discussion on
this paper
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is recorded in archive live stream
please provide feedback so we can
improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow video etiquette
for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to find out more
about participating in projects and
learning groups
all right we are in live stream 50.2 in
our third discussion on interception as
modeling allostasis as control
and we had a DOT zero background in
context video and two weeks ago now we
had a great number
050.1 discussion
so we're just going to have
introductions of people who were here
last week and then Ian will share
something for a few minutes
and then we'll be discussing whatever
people want so
we can each just say hello and anything
that we want to explore today or some
Reflection from the last two weeks so
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and I'll pass to Dean
thanks Daniel I am Dean I'm here in
Calgary in Canada
and uh
not much to say other than I'm looking
forward to uh getting past the content
which was the zero of the context which
was the one and figuring out what what
we can conceptualize into in the in in
this two I'll pass it over to Jordan
sure so I'm Jordan I'm a postdoc uh
working with the South and Barrett and
Karen quickly at Northeastern
um and I think I've said the last time
that we've done this this paper sort of
emerged out of the energetics reading
group that we've done so I'm broadly
interested in brain energy metabolism
I've been doing some other work on that
and was not here last week uh in the
week between these sessions because I
was at the International Conference on
brain energy metabolism which was very
fun
um and yeah I'm I think I'm excited to
get to the conceptual details of this
paper here too and interest in thinking
about what a control theory model of uh
of the brain and then the terreception
looks like
uh and pass it over to Eli Maybe
hi I'm Eli I'm the first author on the
paper grad student with fion villain
vandement who is sort of our under
mentioned co-author and with Lisa Felton
Barrett and Karen Quigley
I would say that I'm
I just got away from a conversation with
Maxwell ramstead so I'm actually a bit
excited about active inference as a
he really clarified for me what it is
and what it means
um
yeah and I think I could pass to is that
all of us yep or Ian do you still need
to go
hi yes thank you
um so I'm in I'm based in England UK and
um so my background many years ago was
in kind of uh undergraduate of
biochemistry and then pitched in
molecular biology applied to immunology
and how white blood cells can determine
between molecular signals of safety and
threat
um I didn't stay very long with that
moved on to working on Environmental
Management projects and
um
therapy so manual therapy Health
mentoring and related things and in that
World
um a common
kind of
um
theme I noticed was paying attention to
bodily signals and sensing interpreting
bodily signals but I didn't have a way
to
talk about that confidently that made
sense in with the versions of
homeostasis and the autonomic nervous
system that I was taught in the 90s so
when I a few years ago discovered there
was a group of small group of
researchers
studying interception I got very excited
very quickly and I've been involved
recently in a little bit of research on
interest training for improved
interceptive awareness with a university
nearby here and when Daniel shared that
this paper and said you were it was
going to be on the active Insurance
Institute I got goodly excited and
wasn't quite sure why that was so I said
I wouldn't I was trying to figure it out
and watching
55.0 and I asked if I could share a few
pictures which um maybe I'll do now if I
can share screen
to
oh is that going to be possible sure and
I'll crop it so that it's the whole
screen
okay so
um
I thought why was I why was I so excited
to see this paper I hope it might be
able to help people in a therapeutic
world because I know that you've sort of
talked about physiology meeting
engineering but then this is a slightly
different
um
maybe a slightly different take
yeah go full screen or just give me once
oh there we go to yeah give me one
second so um oh is that can you see that
now yep I'm just gonna make it big just
give me one second to get it finished
all right go for it
so in the dot zero I heard um people
talking about baked in reflexes and it
made me think of this these pictures
which were have been going around uh on
the internet of why oh sorry why are
cats scared of cucumbers
um is it because they're born with
um to be scared of snakes so kind of
some kind of genetic you know cucumbers
look like snakes so they go from feeding
mode into
clear mode um or is it that their cruel
owners have just put something
surprising behind them
which um so it's just stimulating a
startle reflex either way I don't know
what the cat's interceptive experiences
but
um there certainly seems to be something
that it
um is automatic is happening there
so um thinking about in the therapeutic
world there's
what's often what we're often trying to
achieve is if something is if a behavior
has become maladaptive and starts to
feel like it's reflexive for a person so
let's say a phobia against spiders or a
phobia against public speaking or a
phobia you know a fear of going into Pub
um
public spaces then the person may feel
like I know I'm going to suffer in this
situation it's just a reflex reaction
but with interceptive exposure therapy
what I find is interesting is that
people
um are able to in the in a safe space
able to say okay
when this thing happens to me I feel
Maybe
short of breath tightness in my chest so
if we can recreate that sensation in a
safe environment can gradually they
learn to change whatever their
predictions or their beliefs are about
what that sensation means and it seems
to work and you know one method of doing
that for if breathing is an issue for
people and that with anxieties to
recreate it by breathing through a straw
so the you know the the aim really is to
turn something maladaptive into a more
adaptive Behavior or a vicious cycle
into a virtual Circle so instead of
triggering this kind of
ought uh reaction which feels unpleasant
and is involved you know
reflexes or supposed reflexes are being
triggered that are linked to shortness
of breath or increased heart rate
instead so they can
um learn to create some changes in the
body that might be associated with
something more pleasurable such as you
know relaxing with family on a beach or
some kind of pleasant situation so
different changes in that autonomic
nervous system
and in general what we you know what we
are sort of interested in doing is using
interceptionism access point to be able
to untangle you know the story the
thoughts that people have
from the situation they're in and the
bodily Sensations that they're sensing
or that are arising so Dean you
mentioned about packing your parachute
this was another kind of image that came
to mind most babies are probably born
with some kind of reaction that stops
them throwing themselves out of high
places but it does seem to be possible
to override any interceptive fear and
for some people even to enjoy throwing
themselves off high places
um likewise we can learn you know we can
learn to that
situations such as maybe sitting in
front of a laptop with an email box full
of emails
for some people can lead to an
interceptive sensation that's like a
sinking feeling or a cramping or you
know a heavy feeling
so then they've learned they weren't
born with that but they've learned to
associate these situations with
something really you know stressful
um
ah this was from the paper I think uh
Jordan or Eli you referred to last year
sorry last week the dot one
um I haven't digested it fully but it
you know it's
it's really becomes apparent that the
the direction of these circles and the
the loops within Loops
um are quite quite complex
but I really liked the way that you just
these are my Reflections now from what
where you ended in dot one which was
this idea of kind of Cooperative control
or optimal control
um
and you know I was sort of taught about
feedback loops as being like thermostats
and uh
you know maybe fat levels in a person's
body
being influenced just by the hormone
leptin for example
um but it seems that the set points in
the settling ranges are much more mobile
than once was thought and we see that
now with you know and involved a lot
more crosstalk so rather than just
targeting something like leptin as the
problem for the Obesity sort of uh
crisis then you know this is just to
start taken from UK government office
which create a CIS an obesity systems
map that identified you know 108
interconnected variables that determine
people's energy balance in relation to
in obesity and some of those things
might include marketing and advertising
social pressures
um so how do we you know how do we
bring all of those things in to these
types of models that are being created
um and then there's epigenetic factors
as well so you know people can inherit
their exposome through epigenetic
changes and can that change their
interceptive predictions
and you know how I think about this from
a kind of Health mentoring or coaching
what if this I'm not quite sure if I've
wrapped my head around time averaged the
concept of time averaging completely but
you know if I have someone comes to me
and they say
we're talking about the health and they
want to be healthy enough in 20 years
time to be able to support their
grandchildren and play with their
grandchildren then that's if that's a
strong enough interceptive signal of
pleasure into the future you know or
strong enough desire can that override
the short-term interceptive prediction
of
um Bliss which
is may be achieved from some you know
very predictably produced junk food
that's been designed to create a
prediction of you know an interceptive
anticipatory
um pleasurable sensation how do those
over time how do those two different
kind of competing desires work with each
other
is it a battle of will or what you know
some of them seem really deeply reflects
they both seem deeply reflexive but they
are often at odds with each other
um
and again with this kind of time
averaging I was thinking about in in the
allotment this isn't from my allotment
but um you know plants when they're
stressed they bolt earlier and flower
early if they think their environment is
dry or not haven't got enough root
nutrients or enough space for the The
Roots then they will flower early go to
seed early so
um is that what uh time averaging is
related to and the other thoughts was
about this idea of um someone mentioned
about exercise being good for you
because it's a short-term stressor and
it helps your heartbeat slower over the
long term I see lots of sort of people
talking about homiesis in the health and
fitness and hometric stresses in the
health and fitness kind of Arena but we
don't seem to have a good model of it or
a way of telling what The Sweet Spot is
for a hermetic stressor
um
yes and there's lots of you know people
doing hormetic stresses at the moment
Wim Hof and hot and cold therapy and so
on and the last thing I'm nearly done
the last thing that interested me after
was this idea of ergonicity and the
distinction you made in this paper
between our Golic and nanogotic sort of
ergotic systems and I was at a park run
last Saturday and talking to some of the
people my friends at the Finish
um
about how difficult it is to you know
you can feel like you're interceptively
feel like you're running really bad one
day but then your time is actually
quicker than what you expect another day
you can be really up for it and excited
and feel buzzing and you get to the
finish line and realize you've gone
slower
um this picture is from someone who
wrote broke the the world record
um achieved a marathon in under two
hours and part of the tools in their
toolbox was to have a laser to keep
their speed constant throughout the the
marathon so you know the both at any
point either in one instance or
throughout the whole Marathon they their
time was constant so I guess my question
is is technology if if we've if we're
trying to design systems based on the
idea of ergodicity will are we reverse
engineering that into our lives maybe
um
and where would that lead if you've seen
the the film don't look up and it's all
about prediction and modeling
um
What will what will we be evolving into
if we don't have you know the right
systems that are truly matching uh
biological what's actually happening
with our biology and um yeah that was
they're my reflections
that's great
awesome Ian thanks for bringing all of
that that's really insightful so I think
we have more than enough to just begin
so let's just start with whoever wants
to reflect please Jordan first
I mean yeah I guess I can this will be
going a little bit off of the paper here
but I think just what you were bringing
up is is interesting to um
some of the other work that I've been
doing as well too and what we can think
of
we can think of sort of extending the
systems that we're talking about this
paper outside of the body right so some
of what you were bringing up was you
were talking about um
some of the sort of social feedback that
you get for
um maintaining allostasis
um you were bringing up the example of
email and the sort of enteroceptive
response that you can get from
anticipating
um stress from from email from
communication these sorts of things and
you're talking about how there's
how
external references and you were giving
the example of technology and a laser to
keep Pace on a marathon can help
um
can basically act as an external you can
use external reference signals right and
I think one way to think about social
influence or certain some of the social
forces on enteroceptive experience is
also as like external reference signal
Striders at least as external factors
and so the um
I think
one thing so you could think about the
the example of the email that you were
giving is it's an interesting case right
because you basically have um
in some ways you're kind of opening
yourself up to this import to this
portal of potential interceptive
disruption that can arrive at any moment
and that's not going to be
um
it's not going to have some of the usual
uh
contingencies that would allow you to
predict it like you would in other cases
like if you're going to a meeting
did you go into your if you're going to
go meet with your boss and you know it's
at four o'clock
you know that none of the sort of social
signals from that that could potentially
be something you have to react to
something that you have to adapt in a
Terrace up the state to something that's
going to cause you to have to
leverage or basically mobilize your body
to respond to that situation those
aren't going to happen until about four
o'clock when you go to that meeting
if you're open to email
you're basically going to be able to be
prompted within any sort of work hour so
you need to be prepared for that
potential mobilization at any point
right
if your boss is like a real you know
if your boss is really awful then maybe
you're going to get emails in the middle
of the night and if that's the case then
you need to be prepared for some sort of
some sort of allostatic mobilization at
literally any point of the day
which is going to bring with itself some
sort of consequences of needing to have
this system in a state of preparedness
um because disruptions could come at any
point right
and so I think the um
if one of the principles that's an Eli's
paper here right is that
we're defining
putting together an allostatic response
as being
[Music]
um
keeping variables at multiple levels of
this control system in a state where
they can be maximally responsive to the
sorts of threats that could emerge then
that's going to look very different if
you're constantly in a state where you
need to be prepared for a lot of
different disruptions that could come in
from social sources
versus if you're in a state where you
could rule some of those things out you
know it's the weekend in New York you
know your boss or colleagues aren't
going to call you and so you can not
have to have some of these variables in
a state of preparedness to immediately
react to those sorts of things right
um but that's that's all that made me
immediately think of and I think I I
could go on and on because I have some
other work that's on sort of social
social ballastasis or social influence
and how we can impact people through
that but maybe I should pass over to Eli
because I feel like I've
I've set you up to think about how maybe
this is relevant to to what we're doing
right in terms of
being prepared for an Adaptive response
and how different contexts can
can change that right
thank you
Eli want to go for it
I think you're muted sorry
I found really interesting the thing
with the laser actually and I'm sort of
wondering
how that how those metabolic trade-offs
are taking place in the brain of a
runner because you know normally the
evidence shows that people will adjust
their gait or their running speed to
sort of optimize their allostatic
Challenge and therefore their energy
efficiency
and here it looks as though the point of
the laser is that you keep the actual
speed constant which means you're
letting the level of allostatic
challenge of the enteroceptive
sensations vary a lot
or at least a lot more in order to keep
the actual speed constant and I'm
wondering how this can like how this can
happen in the brain like that you
construct this alternative sensory
variable that you control
instead of the interceptive sensations
and what
sort of where how motivation can be
grounded in in terreception
to spend this extended time undergoing
interceptive challenge
but could it also be too that you're
because
part of
part of this right is that we talk about
and this was Ian you were talking a bit
about
um
with uh
interceptive feed or so in terms of the
feedback or the sense of therapies that
you can do with this that we you can try
to train people to have some more
interceptive awareness
um on the sensory end of it
than they typically or you know to
basically attune people to having some
enteroceptive awareness and then Eli do
you think with the laser Maybe
are you giving people
you're basically
you're giving people something that
might be a more High Fidelity like
sensory signal
like if they're going to try to keep
this laser at sort of center of eye
fixation they need to move at a certain
speed and there's other
there's other variables that can follow
from something that's more easily
tracked in the external environment
whereas it might be more difficult to
keep on
tight tight like sensory control over
some of the anteroceptive signals you
can you can structure that for people so
it's a little bit easier Maybe
well I mean yeah I I sorry I was just
thinking that the laser
um is teaching them to ignore their
interceptive signals actually
um to place more emphasis on
a constant speed required to win than it
is on you know oh my you know my legs
are feeling a bit heavy or
I'm feeling a bit dehydrated or you know
um I'm feeling a bit hot
so they're ignoring those and
focusing more on the outside world
um
can I just ask a question because I know
I always take it from the I'm the real
novice here
and I think sometimes that that can add
something to this what if the laser is
has it has an offloading
so the top down
bottom up that that back and forth that
that
you guys with your paper really clearly
said there's two directions here in this
enteroception what if what if the
offloading interrupts
that
back and forth and simply because you're
offloading it now you aren't creating
that
it it it's not it's not external it's
it's at it it's added not even as a move
a move to that center point on the
sigmoid curve it's simply acting as a
proxy
and and in in in in
approximating for you that's taking less
energy for yourself now you can consume
the calories in running or you can
consume the calories in trying to keep
things within a range and if you're not
burning up calories to try to keep
things within a range you can now apply
those calories to the running
if I could uh give a thought on just
that there's so much to add to I'm
thinking of where else are there lasers
in tasks like running
and it makes me think about the task as
the offloading
that principle of a small task expanding
to the amount of time that you have
that's more in the cognitive domain like
if you have five minutes to write the
email you have five minutes if you have
an hour you have an hour and then
similarly with moving a pile of dirt or
doing some physical task when the only
thing that's being considered
is the decision to do it somebody might
surprise themselves with backpacking or
undertaking
allostatic challenge
under the task structure of
something that's external so like the
laser it's already set
versus uh
without that
desire or capacity to undertake that
allostatic challenge it doesn't present
itself as an affordance at all
so there's just um
and then also a really interesting was
the note about Ian you added about how
some days you feel very good but you're
speed or amount lifted might be lower
and vice versa
so
in the models as presented does the
entity have a true
interception
so what is that difference with the
experience
and performance and Valence
of a given allostatic load
well I'm not sure I'm I'm not sure if I
can answer that question but I think the
thinking about
one thing that's going to happen if
you're going to continue to run for a
long time right is that there's going to
be certain
there's going to be certain motor
signals you're going to have to give and
there's going to be certain sensory
feedbacks that are going to come from
that partly in terreceptive information
and the problem is that if you're
wearing yourself out over the course of
a marathon those are going to be moving
targets right
there's not going to be some consistent
amount of force that you're going to
need to apply and as your muscle weakens
as you're running for longer and longer
the amount of force is potentially going
to have to change so it's
going to become difficult to
to keep even a consistent speed right
you're going to have to actually vary
the amount of force in the actual motor
commands are going to have to be given
[Music]
um
and if you don't get
[Music]
um
if a lot of the feedback that you're
getting from that isn't isn't especially
precise right because you're moving
along the road the environment's moving
around you it's difficult to get some
consistent reference point for it and so
what the laser is doing right is it's
basically giving you on
some sort of constant that you can
um
that you can regulate in lieu of having
to perform the calculations to regulate
a lot of other stuff that's changing in
your body and over the entire period of
it right it's and I think about it in
terms of you do a similar thing with
like a metronome or something like that
as well right where if you're trying to
coordinate a lot of different people to
perform musical notes in time you'd want
to have a conductor you'd want to have
um
you there's there's a real use in having
external reference points for managing
those things because
literally everything in your body is
changing as you're performing this stuff
and commands need to be connect commands
need to be given to
to regulate in the face of all of that
change Eli's pointing so I think Eli's
got a point
um yes I mean I was just gonna say like
we know that as you move a bunch of your
sensory and interceptive signals change
so they're basically never actually
constant in the first place if there's
something you want to hold constant then
yeah you need something like laser that
effectively gives you an artificial
source of constancy a source of
conscious constancy outside the body
because you don't have one internally
[Music]
yes
yeah and it's what what's also occurring
to me
um as you're saying that is as well as
the
internal conditions changing you know
the the external conditions are changing
and you know it may be getting windier
at various points of the course
um and there may be you know uh Daniel
you talked about
um when we spoke a while ago about ants
if they when it appropriate for them to
react to weather changes and there may
be
you know we want a marathon runner to
essentially ignore all the weather
changes
um and just keep running at the desired
speed so it's almost
um yeah maybe that you know the last
slide I put there was a bit of a a
distraction really
um I don't think it's a distraction at
all though but because I think that the
no I think it's super super useful
because like part of again this whole
idea of um multiple variables in the
body changing all at once that's kind of
core of what we mean when we're saying
allostasis right we're saying that there
aren't any particular constants that are
there there's a lot of variables that
are moving and changing and what Eli's
making the point in this paper is that
in lieu of set points in a lot of those
cases what you want is
some variables to try to occupy a zone
of maximal flexibility to changing
circumstances
um
but
at some point like it there might be
some variables deep deep down in turn
like very very Central to regulating the
body that are going to need to be kept
at some close to homeostatic level and
so one of the things that was coming up
for me in working with the brain energy
metabolism conference is that variables
like blood oxygenation might be one of
those right those are very tightly
regulated if that Strays outside of some
very narrow parameters you're going to
have really serious problems
but if you think about your Runner
running the marathon
the um
that blood oxygenation level is going to
be fluctuating it's going to be
challenged there's going to have to be
responses or other compromises made in
the body to maintain that
and if that's the very if that's one
variable that's being kept at a type
that's being tightly regulated at the
core of interceptive information
[Music]
other compromises that are going to
happen to regulate that down the line
might be changes in muscle Force
delivered changes in speed a lot of
fluctuations that are happening in terms
of how they're moving their body through
this race and so if you're giving them
some external external sensory signal to
couple to basically at the other end of
this control hierarchy that Eli's
describing right then you're giving them
something at the other end of it to
couple to to make their movement through
the environment a bit more regulated and
predictable so you could think of it as
the entire control hierarchy that Eli's
describing in this paper
we have some very closely regulated
terreceptive values far to the left
we have a deep net of predictions and
prediction error throughout the entire
cortex that's performing some regulation
um across the entire network and then we
have exteroceptive information at the
other end of it and what you're doing
with the lasers you're basically giving
the organism the goal of fixing some of
those values at the exteroceptive layer
to give some more structure as they move
throughout this entire
deep deep Network in all the space
between it right
yes
and what I'm thinking also there you
know what the marathon runner did before
that Marathon so the marathon was made
predicted his work his
breaking that record was made easier for
him by the laser but also you know maybe
he
influenced his blood his blood
oxygenation you know this the upper and
lower limits of the acceptable settling
range by doing
um altitude training to stimulate more
um right red blood cells he might have
done Hyperbaric therapy
um to all those things which will make
it easier for him just to follow that
later right and I guess an Eli's
framework right that would be that's not
necessarily changing the settling point
of blood oxygenation but what it is
doing is at variables that are just
slightly levels down from that you're
Eli would this be right to say you're
basically widening out that sigmoid
function so that there's more
adaptability
um from that additional training for
increasing red blood cells that sort of
thing is that right
yeah definitely
I'd also sort of add that
some physiological variables are very
tightly regulated
but one of the open questions is
sort of how how many removes are they
from a disturbance
so like blood oxygenation or the pH in
the brain that you mentioned
you know what does it actually take to
disturb those
right
like what oxygenation you can probably
disturb by just having greater or lesser
uptake of oxygen from the blood brain pH
I'd imagine that
honestly I'd imagine that you have to
disturb a lot of things sort of
disturb your way through the outer
control system like the outer several
layers of control systems possible
before you can actually
perturb that but you can think about
things like the fact that you have a
blood-brain barrier in the first place
is one thing that might help keep that
sort of thing tightly regulated right
exactly that's what I mean is that yeah
you know living systems tend to be sort
of homeostatic or allostatic at
every level
like a cell maintains its own internal
you know homeostasis in some sense
or allostasis by interchange with its
environment then an organ system may
also have you know such as the brain may
have the blood-brain barrier
you know and sort of other levels of
protection that insulated from its
environment right
because it has to be in cooperation with
other organ systems for sure and I guess
the thing that I'm saying is just that
the four
for some of those parameters that do
need to be really tightly regulated like
that right you might see some
some
uh
some naturally developing physiological
structures like the blood-brain barrier
that are there to help keep those values
tightly regulated
as opposed to having it be
more under behavioral control in which
case there's some there's some
flexibility there's some allostatic
flexibility in those right
the what you want is if there's
something that really really has to be
kept at a certain level
you would ideally have some of the
evolved biology work to
fix some of those parameters in the
physiology itself maybe what do you
think
I'm sorry actually could I
just take my dog out for five minutes
sorry she's really begging me quite a
lot and like the space is getting to me
go ahead go ahead Jordan I was just
gonna joke about I want to go find a
cucumber and try that out of my cat too
yeah actually um Terry in the chat wrote
Irish cats don't do this there are no
snakes in Ireland seriously I've tried
it with our cat oh so not all cats well
and our cats lived in Doris for her
entire life except for the first six
weeks or so which was probably blind for
half of that so I should try it out on
her too and see if there was some
learning component to it or if she
if she has it innate
[Music]
sorry dude yeah go ahead Dean I just
wanted to kind of throw this in here and
I don't know I'm feeling kind of bad
because Eli's walking his dog but I'm
sure he'll he'll pick up right here so
in the in the dot one I brought up this
idea and I'm not sure how often it's
it's not ubiquitous yet but I I think
that the focus in this paper is about
perspective swaps so what do I mean by
that I kind of want to just do a quick
lap around that ergotically and then see
what you guys think about this so
offloading to a laser as as a
perspective uh in the dot zero Daniel
saying staying within the connection
space as he was talking about CDF to PDF
as being another type of perspective
taken
um the idea of bringing psychologists
and their perspectives and engineers and
their perspectives together in in an
Institute or a lab setting as a as a
different type of that
different perspectives colliding or at
least paralleling
um yeah dance dodgeball opposing teams
each having a different perspective
because they're wearing a different
Penny
um instrumental that one of the things
we would talk about a lot in active
inference is instrumentalism and and an
action or the idea of um sort of the
embodied Space versus the theoretical
the map yeah perspective and the
territory perspective
um and and in this paper's case the
specific feedback control Focus as a
perspective right what I'd like to do is
take that idea that there's all these
perspectives that one can be swapped in
and swapped up within the idea of
Regulation within ranges yes but I'd
like to talk a little bit about what Ian
brought up which is I think is a really
critical point and maybe quite
complementary not corollary but
complementary to what the paper was
talking about you you said if we do
something in a safe
space now to me I'm going to ask you
this
to me safe sometimes means controlled
meaning the Agents Set the condition or
at least they proceed they have some
control over that condition
okay so that's a perspective
that's sometimes perceived as ergotic
because it's predictable
right then we have
a sense of how do we strategize from
that set condition one that's
variability reduced
to one that's conditioned set or
variability retained and I use the
example that you had on one of your
slides which is 108 interconnected
variables that determine dot dot dot
because to me that's what this paper is
trying to focus on that specific
feedback control is that shift in
perspective that swap between the
variability reduced
because that's what that's what I said
variability retained for me as a skier
was I've got an open field it's pristine
it's 12 12 inches deep and away I go but
as more trees start amassing my ability
to be free because of
variability my my variability Factor
changes and now the ignition set is my
pers my perspective swap has to be can I
continue or am I just going to end up
bashing into a bunch of Limbs right
right so the bringing of the two
together to me I want to kind of make
clear what I mean by perspective swap
yeah I don't think it contradicts what
you've written in the paper I think the
move from CDF to PDF
is a perfect example of that perspective
Swap and I'm not sure it's just a
derivative because as I said in the last
live stream you bring you bring
psychologists and Engineers into the
same space and one doesn't get to rule
over the other you need both to create
that that swapping condition
right right
so right
is that is that essentially what
specific feedback control
helps us get a better sense of not just
a grip or an optimality but sort of a a
clear separation so that we can do the
oscillating so that we can do the
swapping and so that when we're having
these kind of interactions we're not
doing a transdisciplinary thing here
we're really trying to get our heads
around why did the laser work
right
I think because we can perspective swap
that we might get closer to something
satisfactory
so
I'm trying to understand so when you're
talking about a perceptive or perception
swamp
I don't know if I'm going to answer your
question satisfactionally we might have
to wait for Eli but I'm going to try my
best here because I'm not the that's all
I want you know because I try my best
too that's because nobody's got to be
perfect right right and I think but I
think that that's part of what factors
into what I was gonna how I was gonna
try to answer here which is that I think
that
um
foreign
so the way I'll try to answer this is
I'll try to draw in some of the social
some of the social realistic stuff that
I've done which is involving more like
you're saying interactions between
people if we're bringing psychologists
and Engineers together this sort of
thing so
if let's say just
if I answered your question right now
let's let's pretend that I answered your
question in a way that
precisely got to the core of it and just
stopped the conversation
and you just said oh yeah I got it that
answers it in a word right
then I might have percepted I might have
perception swapped slope so closely to
the way that you would frame this
question and so perfectly understood
that the way that you'd asked it right
that we don't actually explore the space
around it in a way for other people to
come in to understand anything of what's
going on exactly
if I actually didn't totally understand
your question I need to ask questions
that we need to bounce this back and
forth for like several minutes then
we might still come to a settling point
and we might perform some gradient
descent to come to a natural answer here
but because it's going to take longer it
might end up bouncing around through
different parts of the space of answers
that we could look at and end up
capturing other ways that um other
perspectives might be able to understand
it right so that they can catch some
element of it that was predictable or
that fit with some internal model that
they'd already generated and then to be
able to follow along to the gradient
descent to reach down to that point
right
so I think that part of the advantage
right of having interdisciplinary
conversations and we've done this a lot
especially you know in working with Eli
and then working with the engineers at
Northeastern these psychology engineer
interdisciplinary collaborations right
is that
there will be a really long and
frustrating period where people just do
not understand each other
um
and you need to actually work through
that because that's a period where you
can do some learning and you can
actually
get some understanding of other
perspectives other ways to build a model
of the environment other ways to sort of
take a perspective on events that are
actually happening
but
um
there will be a Temptation through the
entire thing to cut your losses and
leave it because it is frustrating and
it is metabolically costly I'd say
um to do all of that information
processing and to follow that process
and it's not always obvious when the
gradient descent is going to end either
or when you do understand each other or
when everyone has sort of followed into
the loop and you're able to follow that
down to make the environment predictable
to come to a shared understanding
um
you know it could have you might know
when you're getting close but until you
get to that point you might be in a
really long and frustrating process of
of search prediction error
uh
of uh of basically bouncing around
through the environment of trying to to
come up with some model that can predict
it right yeah so I feel like that was a
very meta way of trying to answer your
question but I think does does that help
I think there's a I think it gets it
part of the use of of interdisciplinary
work right and
at how we uh
how having these different perspectives
are gonna
help us explore the space more fully
because if we
if we just had an internal language to
each other and if we perfectly
understood each other in the first place
then like you don't actually end up
exploring the space in that case because
you descend to
you descend to sort of common
predictions too fast to to Really bounce
around and explore everything you've
just you've basically described the
capitulation to a retroductive or an
abductive logical process that's all
you've done and I don't think there's
anything
to ask you about that it's been around
for over 100 years and and I think it's
having a Renaissance so thank you cool
cool cool
oh Ian
oh yes as you were talking there about
this you know um
different disciplines coming together it
was reminding me of
um one of the
active instruments institutes uh papers
that were covered a few weeks ago on uh
social communication as control I think
it was
um and also reminding me of you know the
difficulty
of a newborn child and a parent
um you know that all the child can do is
cry when it's
feels some sort of discomfort and then
the parent has to try and figure out
what that
cry means does it mean it's hungry does
it mean it's
um nappy needs changing doesn't mean
it's too hot or cold so there's a
there's a period of learning each
other's language and learning what each
other's cues are
and regulating each other and
controlling each other
um yeah that's what you know arguably
that's all we're doing all the time as
as socially as adults we've just got a
more bigger set of vocabulary and
um we can influence our environment more
than the baby well then we can tell each
other what our
what our expectations are too right like
the baby is giving a really diffuse
signal that there is some interceptive
states disrupted and then the adult has
to like we were saying right explore
around and bounce around until they can
Converge on that and
get the baby satisfied satisfy that
interroceptive state right
but
you know if I
so some of the other work that I've done
is looking at how I really want to look
at this paper then of uh of social
communication is controlled because
that's related to some other stuff that
I've been doing too but it's that um
I think that
you can think of social influence as um
basically people regulating uncertainty
in a social environment by um conforming
to predictions that other agents have in
it
so you can think of a social Norm as a
set of collective expectations that
people might have in an environment
um and if you conform to those
expectations then you can minimize
prediction error for people and you can
minimize the likelihood that their
behavior is going to change that your
environment is going to become disrupted
more entropic anything like that
and so
the babies basically creating
uh
entropy in their environment for the
adults in the room to try to minimize by
satisfying interceptive needs for them
you can as an adult once you can
communicate maybe get around some of
those problems by saying you know
you ask someone to pass the salt of
Thanksgiving or pass you know past the
butter
you've made an expectation extremely
clear and then people can satisfy that
expectation and everything continues on
predictably right they could also refuse
and say
no I'm not going to pass the song
but if you do that you will move things
onto a more unpredictable trajectory
right you're going to
uh push things out of the sort of bounds
that people are used to navigating and
you're going to potentially move off
into this
space that's having to explore each
other's reactions like like Dean was
talking about right
yes yeah and what you're sort of saying
there it's reminding me of um some of
the work so it's a great research
researcher called Demetrius ziolet
gatas I think he's he's done a lot of
work on ritual and um how
rituals basically you know he's put
heart rate monitors on people and
measured cortisol levels and so on over
you know the weeks and days following
rituals
and showing that it's you know there's a
lot of synchronization that occurs
during rituals
um but the the so the synchronization of
physiology
but it's bound up in these kind of codes
or rules about how our plan or our group
or our society should operate so it's
kind of I you know my interpretation on
that is it's training a person's
physiology to align itself with
social behaviors
is this wait was this Demetrius bolus
Demetrius
um his surname is spelled
x-y-g-a-l-a-t-a-s he wrote a book
recently called ritual how seemingly
senseless acts make life worth living
but um
yeah he's done some
um
study with measuring you know heart rate
variability and stuff for fire walking
kind of rituals and so on
that's really cool Jordan you did
mention Demetrius bolus and the work
from 2020 through others we become
ourselves the dialect is the predictive
coding active inference also hinging on
a shared first name but a very relevance
paper as well
um and then one thought to connect this
idea of synchrony
uncertainty controlled novelty in
communication
and in rituals that's when
people are the laser for each other
with their attention so then it's like
okay we're gonna do a role play where
this is going to be the case
I'll synchronize this
perspective you'll have this perspective
will just be like it will be just two
stubborn characters having this argument
it'll be very funny
and then that
is a predictable play it could even be
scripted or at the very least you can
have fun and
so on so it's very interesting that
that is reflected in the social space
whereas the marathoning and going for
the record which few people want to do
most people can take a much more relaxed
approach
than the person trying to set the world
record but in the social space uh as
Dean brought up
there's a lot that we can bring to bear
on the social space
from variability reduced settings like
laboratory studies on cognition fmri
studies with social stimuli
but the social space is a variability
retained
area of application
right and so but we yeah with the
translation yes Jordan
but but social norms right or sort of
some social standards or Mutual
expectations
add some variability constraint to that
social space right because there's
nothing physically stopping you from
doing a lot of different things in any
social setting
but the point is that if you want to
stay in a variability reduced space
and I think that there's some metabolic
advantages in enteroceptive advantages
to staying in a metabolically returning
variability reduced state right
then
it's just the predictions of other
agents that
um
set some of the bounds of where you'll
wander into a variability increase state
if you wander outside of those
expectations or a variability reduce
state if you stay within them right so
as long as you're adhering to some
predictions that other agents would have
in that environment
then you're going to stay in a
variability reduced State and you can
say you can stay for lots of purposes
sort of socially invisible to other
agents you don't need to create
new disruptions to an environment that
you're going to need to be prepared to
adapt to right
thank you Dean
sorry I'll blew over my hand again so
the fascinating thing about the paper
was I used a basic heuristic that says
when in doubt and we're pretty much
always in doubt zoom in zoom out
and so when I when I look at the scale
of what that would mean from uh the
perspective of interception those time
scales are much tighter than if I zoom
it out to the allostasis involved in
running a marathon my zoom in zoom out
range and potential gain is much
different for the allostasis than it is
for the tarot section that's involved
over that same course of time
and so that's where I found the specific
feedback control which implies that
there must be a general feedback control
as well
so interesting that's where Eli's part
about the four different time
segmentation possibilities allows for
that zoom in zoom out
um does that
am I contradicting what the point was
that you were trying to make in the
paper Eli
um I'm I am slightly wondering where you
got four specific scales
well you have The L4
in terms of oh yeah oh that was just for
modeling purposes no I understand that
but I mean you can still you can still
inflate that to yeah yeah
but I think that's a pretty standard
part of the hierarchical act of
inference literature isn't it yeah
okay
but do you think the idea that again we
can swap from from the specific to the
general is again it just seems to be
again and again it's that ability to
move within
ranges but but the range doesn't
necessarily
remain consistent unless of course
you're following a laser but that goes
back to my original question is because
we offload the the metabolic commitment
that we would have to
stay at that level of consistency we can
then turn those resources over to other
aspects of that endeavor
let me try to ask that a different way
to Jordan I think would be
um would be how would different patterns
in
this type of a multi-time scale framing
reflect different metabolic or energetic
costs like does the brain use more
oxygen glucose
Ketone bodies micronutrients
who knows during what kind of activity
such that there's what kind of a link
between the
physiological costs
in gold
yeah versus that means cognitive angle
I mean I think the way to to do it and
this was I think um I was thinking of
this when you ask Eli too is that the
the trick is right is that if you're
regulating
um
some of the input to
the interceptive input that you're
trying to regulate that might be really
Central to allostatic regulation right
could be from sensed and terreceptive
variables
uh like you know like blood oxygenation
like blood glucose
but the trick is right is that and this
is that I think more what I'm interested
in what I'm trying to develop with
thinking about brain metabolism is that
all of the steps and all of the
communication that has to be done at
some of these lower orders of this
hierarchical scale right isn't free it
has metabolic costs itself right and so
you know in the human brain the actual
resting state cost of the human brain
when it's just you're just sitting still
in the MRI scanner is about 20 of your
body's metabolic budget
um it fluctuates a little bit as you're
doing some sort of uh
as you're doing sensory processing as
you're dealing with unpredictable
information
the details of how it fluctuates like
those matter too and we can get into
those
um there's relative changes in how much
glucose you're consuming versus whether
you're consuming the glucose with oxygen
for like a more efficient yield of of
ATP energy but but the point is just
that neuronal signaling itself is super
expensive and if you're navigating an
unpredictable environment then you can
expect to have some of those expenses
kick up or have them change in ways that
are going to have to be regulated so
what that means right is that
even though there's a hierarchy of
processing here where you're taking in
sensory signals you're passing them up a
cortical hierarchy and you're
compressing them if you're doing that
more and more and if you're an
environment where you have to be passing
potentially more and more prediction
error up this chain
that Canon itself then be changing
um important and terreceptive sensed
variables that might enter at different
points of the hierarchy because there's
still sense information but they might
be more centrally regulated they might
have Downstream effects if those start
to go out of whack right so
basically I think that it you brought up
to that you know thinking about this
from an allostatic perspective instead
of a computational perspective and I
think
the computer metaphor that people have
been using for the brain
kind of computer scientists don't often
think about cost in lots of ways too
unless you know but they'll think maybe
about time cost of how many cycles this
like deep neural net is going to take to
train but they often don't think about
the fact that like
all of the components of this computer
do take like real energy to run and you
know you can heat up the planet mining
Bitcoin you can do all of this stuff too
there's external there's uh
uh external cost to all of this that
aren't taken into account when you're
actually training these systems
the brain can't ignore that because it
is an actual biological system and its
whole point is that it's going to have
to keep that system working navigate the
environment and grab metabolic resources
to keep the cycle going and so um
all of this computation that you're
doing yeah isn't free it adds up and
then can uh
potentially have Downstream effects on
on sensed metabolic variables that are
critical
yeah
great thank you Ian
uh thank you yeah I was just thinking
then after
um what Jordan was saying about you know
climate change and
um that if that's a prediction that's
maybe you know two decades ago wasn't
gonna affect my life
but it might affect the lives of my
children or my children's children to
act now with that that's a that's a very
abstract you know there's probably for
most people there was nothing in their
environment that would
um give them that prediction of future
threats in 50 100 years time
so they have to create a very you know
abstract
sort of image of what the planet's going
to be like and then to you know all the
huge energy expenditure that's required
to switch to Renewables to you know
organize Society differently
that's going to require a massive in
allostatic load in the short term
or interceptive sort of yeah demand
chronic low-level interceptive
disturbance
to create that shift through generations
right
and so I think you see right like
there's
if what your brain is regulating is
at the core that some of the
interceptive parameters that are
necessary to keep your body and your
polar organism moving forward right then
being thrown into a constant state of
uncertainty
is going to be costly if we think it's
true that processing all of that
uncertainty is going to have a metabolic
cost attached to it and so
there's going to be some
I think the way that that your sort of
brain as a regulator is going to work is
probably going to want to return you to
some relatively predictable State and so
the issue right is that if you're if you
require if you could if you could model
and understand externally right like
if you can understand
that in a long that the long-term
trajectory that you're on
in terms of climate change is going to
lead to disaster right
it can still be really difficult to
divert from that because the trajectory
is at least is a predictable trajectory
that you're on until it hits some of
these critical exponential points where
it's suddenly going to break right
and so I think you could see that with
climate change I think you could see
that with the pandemic you can see a lot
of cases where there's um
there's a temptation to return to some
sort of trajectory where when things are
going moment to moment they're
relatively predictable they don't
require a relatively large amount of
attention
um and if you're going to enter into
some uncertain change state
I think you
there's going to be
a sort of collective pressure of a lot
of brains regulated themselves to get
back onto some predictable trajectory
right you can't sustain like complete
uncertainty for a really long time
because
I don't think our brains can handle it
so I would have to ask uncertainty about
what
uncertainty about the immediate lived
environment so what's going on around
you what are you doing when I got up
today like I made coffee I got on the
computer I have a predictable set of
sensory signals that I'm going to be
running into I have yeah yeah like a
daily routine these things I don't mean
yeah yeah
because
let's see so what was it climate change
pandemic so
you know most of these are not actually
things that make your day-to-day life
that unpredictable
that's exactly what I'm saying
I'm saying that those long-term events
those things that you might be worrying
about those things you know that we're
talking about being worried about
climate change they don't actually
impact your day-to-day life right now
very much and so changing your
day-to-day life substantially now to
deal with them is going to be difficult
that's all I'm saying well not
necessarily because the reference
trajectory for
actually dealing with them is not
necessarily that unpredictable either
different from what you're already doing
doesn't mean unpredictable
it's true but the period where you shift
what you're doing to something different
is
and so I guess what I'm saying is that
A change is something that
requires
a difference in trajectory from where
something was already gone
yeah but I think the thing about
so the thing about our trajectory based
formulation of allostasis
is that
well the whole point is that you know if
you let's say you plan to go to the
store you're driving on the road you
make a right turn
is the right turn unpredictable no it's
not it's a predicted baked in part of
the reference trajectory
change does not have to be
unpredictable and I think we should
avoid conflating those two
sure
can I can I bring these first yeah a
couple of examples of things we talked
about in the dot zero so Daniel brought
up a really interesting point when he
talked about um
glucose stacking
and I I automatically sort of brought me
to the idea of people who are have
diabetes and those that are uh I think
it's hypoglycemic unawareness they're
the most brittle diabetics
um and essentially what that speaks to
is they have a large blind spot to sort
of the cumulative effects of what's
going on because the pancreas isn't
working correctly doing that kind of
Regulation piece that blind spot
and the and the severe consequences of
that point but
again I don't want to beat this like
like a dead animal but
because you are blind to something
implies that you cannot take up that
perspective and then the consequences of
that are more severe when you absolutely
don't know how your body is going to
respond to that donut
or not
right so again it's it's we talked about
it in the in the in the context of it
Jordan was really good and clarifying we
can't think of this in economic terms
but I think we can think of it in terms
of blind spot
terms if we have a blind spot to this
how do we respond to it how do seven
billion people respond to it if well
what they do is they revert back to the
to the now
that's what they do about their blind
spot right because they just don't want
to take up the perspective swap because
it's way too challenging
they might also sense there might be you
might think of it also to write in this
control hierarchy of that um
if you're missing uh
an ability to sort of sense and regulate
some parameters in the hierarchy there
might be Downstream consequences of of
glucose use that can be sensed but the
problem is it's going to mean that you
don't have as tight control you're
basically like you're saying you have a
blind spot in that hierarchy that isn't
as tightly regulated and so
it could potentially wander out of some
of the bounds that are going to be
uh adaptive or safe because you're
performing some sort of second order
control on it instead of um controlling
it more tightly with some of the senses
that you would normally use right yeah
but what do you think Ela
if I could just give one quick response
actually on this idea
um The Leverage point of the control
system is the true control variable so
beyond being a good regulator having a
volume knob in your head if there's a
volume knob in the generative process
the ultimate control situation is to
just have the actual control of the
volume knob and there's cases where
that's possible there's case where it's
not but where it is possible it's the
leverage point and then
Jordan you just pointed to if you're
missing this ability to either
um sense
X like we can't directly perceive our
glucagon circulating level or
responsivity across different tissues
it's just too multi-faceted and
subliminal
of an enteroception directly
different hormone balances and so on
though technology and measurements are
increasingly allowing that to be laser
focused
without the ability direct to directly
control those subliminal factors to
either sense or act on them
we can only apply upstream or Downstream
control so we could
modify our niche
or use signposting or stigma G so that
our environment dissuades us or makes
something impossible
like time boxing or just putting
something away
or Downstream consequences like if like
um having um a some kind of supplement
that helps with lactose digestion
so
we can't regulate most you can't put
oxygen in the blood simply
you can't simply change amount of
cholesterol
and so actually being able to have a
framework such as you're describing
where we can talk about
the true physiological variable
the actual substance of the essential
variable
but also recognize that we're only going
to have interceptive access
into potentially noisy or variable
proxies that are influenced by many
things
and they're going to be like sometimes
multiple steps up or Downstream
like lightheadedness in the context of
glucose regulation but that can happen
for a lot of reasons so it can't be
simply the cue
so really interesting
there
um Eli or anyone else
so
I think we have to differentiate between
how could you build an active inference
control system in general
and how are nervous systems built in
specific
how how our nervous system is built in
specific is an empirical question
and I have pretty strong doubts that
it's all just a matter of Leverage
through pretty much the same reason that
I have my doubts about it's all about
avoiding change
like there's just such wide variability
of behavior in real life
there are people who Embrace change
there are people who challenge
themselves
you know there are people who give up
some of their leverage or control over
some things
and if we don't look at those
if we sweep those actual behavioral
instances under the rug of a sort of
General principle
that says well everyone ought to be very
controlling and conservative all the
time
then
I can't help but think it's a sort of
scientific sin
so so you like Dean and I were talking
when you were out too about um
by the way
um normally she's a bit more
allostatically resilient but she might
be ill oh
I hope she's feeling better we but we
were talking about because I think that
maybe
maybe there's a misunderstanding because
I don't think that we're saying that
people only want to control or make
their environments perfectly predictable
right I think um
part of what we were talking about right
we were talking about this idea of
Shifting perspectives or this idea of
[Music]
how do uh
so you're coming at it from the
perspective of what a collaboration
between psychology and Engineering
really gets you in the first place even
right
and what we were talking about is that
part of what it does
if people have the goal of trying to
understand each other at the end of it
and reach some sort of mutual
predictability right so that they've
developed some understanding that they
could build a forward model from that
they can actually
uh they have a model of
um of the environment that incorporates
some understanding from the the other
collaborator right
there's going to be a period of that
where you don't necessarily understand
each other super well
and there's going to be a long period of
speaking to each other and not totally
making sense and having to ask a lot of
questions and having to search the space
and what we are talking about is that
from the perspective of fully exploring
a space to actually develop a complete
model of it
or at least a better model of it
there's actually some advantage of not
having things
um quickly achieve that predictability
for each other
if you quickly just gravitate you know
if I answer a question and the other
person just like immediately understood
what I meant by it
it might be because you know I answered
it in a way that just happened to nail
it for that one person but no one else
in an audience is going to be able to
understand it no one else who's
listening in is going to be able to
understand it and so by having some sort
of imperfect process of gravitating
towards
making things predictable for each other
you know we actually achieved some more
explanation exploration and we sort of
get a better sense of the space that
we're actually moving through and we
might generate a better model than we
would if we just immediately converged
right
yeah of course
but I think yes oh sorry I'll go ahead
BYU raised
the difference between these two
questions how is the nervous system
built in specific or in particulars and
how can you build or what is an active
inference model in general so maybe
return to the top
question
um sure yeah so
I think this is one of those things that
can get a little conflated when we have
these collaborations of psychologists
and engineers
where from the engineering side if
you're building something for
uh so to speak the other acronym that
you can form out of active inference
you know AI instead of active
then you don't want something that works
like a human nervous system necessarily
well you may want to share you know a
few properties but actually you're
building it to solve some sort of task
or to exhibit some sort of relatively
well-specified behavioral routine
and
therefore it's going to be
in most respects very completely
different from a human being
and that's actually not just because
you're trying to avoid
um what is it rossum's Universal robots
right
where of course those were actually made
of flesh and blood
like it's not because you don't want
your computer to grow feelings and
decide to go on strike it's because
apriori there's no reason to build a
machine that works like a person in the
first place
maybe it would decide to go on strike
but
you know the space of things that you
can build is just so much larger
that what you would usually do as an
engineer is just aim towards the point
of the space that you actually need for
your task
and that also implies a sort of Converse
proposition
which is that the human nervous system
is a pretty specific point in a space of
things that could have evolved
or even in the space of things that did
evolve
you know human being versus
what is it it's not a sponge it's that
sea organism mentioned in the one of
those Christian papers
that you know when it goes through a
certain life transition
it latches itself down onto a rock and
goes through a little stage of
metamorphosis where it eats its nervous
system
yeah C squirt thank you man
[Music]
like those both evolved there is some
space of possibilities that includes
both the c squared and the human being
this implies that it's a pretty broad
space of possibilities
and if we're using active inference to
model them both
this implies a very very large space of
possible active inference
models formalisms controllers
so um Eli uh if I've heard you correctly
they you
you're sort of saying that
artificial intelligence or tools that
humans make
um that might be
modeled may or may not be modeled using
active inference um
they you know there's usually a an
outcome or a goal that's that that we
that's quite clear why we build them so
it might be I don't know I want to build
a coffee maker to make me coffee
um and I might use some you know very
intelligent
um methods to to build that coffee
machine but the out the outcome is clear
seems to me that with the nervous system
we're still not clear on what the
outcome is so if it's you know if if the
fep is right then it's just to minimize
free energy minimize surprise but am I
right you're sort of questioning whether
that is the
that is the cup of coffee we're after at
the end
um
yeah and so we always have to sort of
remember
that
dog walker just got here
um we always sort of have to remember
that surprise means under a certain
generative model
and so the models that are present in
free energy can involve
sort of epistemic
value you know like
uh what's it called
verisimilitude to the sensory world
accurate modeling they can also involve
a reference trajectory
and so they can also you know they can
involve both perception and action and
that's a really broad space of things
why are they doing like surprise doesn't
mean a minimized surprise doesn't mean
avoid change
it means minimize you know it means
optimize this information theoretic
functional whose meaning is actually
pretty strictly mathematical
and is the is the outcome always to be
Auto poetic so to make another nervous
system
I mean is it like I don't know that's
what I'm wondering
I would think it usually is
if you're making a coffee maker it
probably isn't
like profit makers sometimes you have to
disassemble them slightly to replace the
parts or to clean them and so you don't
necessarily want it to be
self-organizing in the sense of trying
to what like make another carafe when
you take the carafe away to wash it
foreign
but I think that if Ian's asking about
other places he's asking about
is this something so you're you're
making a distinction you lie between a
living and a non-living system or
between a living system and a tool that
you've made to give it a certain input
and give a certain output back right so
so is maybe just to repeat this question
you know and say for a living system
then do you think that some of the
fundamental control variables here are
are Auto poetic
and there I think I have to say I don't
know because I am not a biologist and I
haven't seen the full range of
weird stuff that other organisms do
and I want to be very very cautious
about the idea
that we can sort of introspect gather
what we think are a few general
principles of human behavior
and you know as as introspections go
they may be pretty good ones and they
may generalize pretty broadly
and then expand that to the entire rest
of the kingdom of living organisms like
the entire rest of the Tree of Life
so just as an easy counter example
there are insects that die when they
mate
this is an ordinary baked in part of
their life cycle
and you know if you want to talk about
that as Auto auto pieces then I think we
have to Auto police this then we have to
ask what is being self-organized the
parent or the child
because the parent empirically is being
disorganized
that's fair I mean I oh sorry not Dean
you should go first
I'm I'm I'm just as happy listening but
I'll just throw this in here because I I
don't know if Eli would describe it this
way I'm certain he wouldn't but I always
like to introduce new ideas
I've always said that if we're talking
about living math now don't make me
Define that if we're talking about
living math math that's a lie that's
much that's to me easier more easily
described as a leap of faith embedded
within a step function rather than being
provided the functional requirements as
a case use and then building the Algos
to carry that through
that's a very clear difference between
the two things one is a bridge and the
other is we all get in a bus build a
ramp and then fly over the The Divide
and then if we're really good and we
land it we go back the other way and go
because we're still
allostatically and homeostatically
existing
but I I to your point I think we have to
be clear that those two things are quite
different
one is a lie and the other is not and
both require math
but not the same math
and even among I would actually caution
even among living systems
living involves
metamorphosis it involves Death at a
certain point it involves reproduction
it doesn't just involve
individual survival
that is not how an ecosystem works
no for sure and I think what I was just
going to add was that I think from an
auto poetic perspective
I don't think anyone would disagree with
that I think that what someone would say
is that you need to think about on
from a perspective of reproducing the
relationships that create an organism
reproduction in that process right could
be a process of recreating the organism
and recreating the structures that
create that organism
when there's components of it that
couldn't be
they couldn't be repaired without
reconstructing the entire thing
basically right
so you have um
you'll have death you'll have any one of
these systems are going to have
components of it that can't
be
can't be repaired
and if if parts of it can't be repaired
then a way of basically
ensuring that that system continues to
exist in the in the relationships that
compose it is to reproduce and create a
new system that has those relationships
but has the parts that are going to
terminally fall into disrepair over a
certain period of Time start fresh so we
can begin that cycle again right
that's actually an empirical Claim about
the evolution of Aging which is that
aging came first
you know at say the Single Cell level
and then reproduction
follows
to cope with that
and I don't know enough about the
history of life to know whether that's
true or not
if I could connect this
very interesting theme
to Dean's
Bridges and ramps which are two
different engineering projects and have
two different
sets of uh structures to modify the
niche with and also Ian's original point
about the epigenome and the exposome and
taking
ecological Developmental and
evolutionary perspectives on human
health
so
um the process of epigenetic
canalization
and the way in which epigenetic
variability can become entrenched
through genomic changes like one protein
that has um a bi-functional aspect over
evolutionary time
when that region undergoes some chance
duplication that could allow those to
Tandem proteins to Diversion functions
and like sub specialize because there's
a new capacity in the genome for the
coding sequence to take on some of the
responsibilities
that had been taken by a protein
modification or some other dual
functionalization of the ancestral
protein so the bridges are on the
Continuum towards modifying the
environment modifying the anatomy to
embody the constraints of the
environment like the buoyancy of a fish
something where the anatomy even without
going into the morphological computation
angle just the scale of the femur is
such that it ends up being able to do
plausible actions which gets you in the
ballpark
by being that kind of thing
and then Behavior takes us closer and
closer to that person jumping off the
plane that Ian showed whether it's like
one footstep
which is
many
times a challenge
for all kinds of various regions I mean
it could be really anything and that's
kind of the challenge of of movement
to the social
risk settings and people having
different profiles or envelopes
of their risk in different areas
of being alone and being with other
people
all these different settings
um
but those are more ramp-like
because in the end especially when it's
socially extended you can't have the
actual bodily
you can't embody
the content of social variability
but your your physical body can embody
the content of being regularized with
the abiotic niche
but the brain can only be prepared
in a way that you know is different from
the body hope that kind of brought it
back to that epigenetics
angle because behavior is even more Epi
than epigenetics and so allostatic are
changes that are faster than it so it
makes sense to put it within a broader
evolutionary perspective on how our
priors got honed in to even this
modality
well in our last um 25 minutes or so
where do we go from dot two
either the researchers or Ian wherever
you feel
um the point you made Daniel about
evolutionary I you know I didn't mention
evolutionary biology specifically at the
beginning but um
for me that seems like a
um maybe a blind spot
here
um
you know I'm thinking also about
Markov blankets and if you you know got
my gut microbiome
um
influencing
my
you know the
um neurotransmitters that I produce and
do I do I include my gut microbiome
in within my Markov blankets and if so
you know what am I feeding my gut
microbiome do I include the food that
I'm selecting within that Markov blanket
and if so do I include the fields that
the food is growing in
um
because that will affect the food and if
so do I include the microorganisms in
the in the soil because that affects the
how the food and then that will affect
the microbes of my gut and that'll
affect me and then do I look at the
weather
so you know it's it's more of a kind of
communion communion of subjects rather
than
um
bound objects
but we have to start somewhere
so it has a bit of a jumping off from
that
I think with all the active inference
work there's always this incredibly
important question which is we can use
the framework across so many different
scales
you know I just had um Maxwell ramstead
tell me that they derived a theorem that
literally every physical system has a
Markov blanket
and then I asked him well how do you
pick out the ones that were interested
in studying
and he said sort of you know basically
he said well there isn't necessarily a
theorem directing you to the most
interesting you know or a metric that
tells you which ones are interesting
so that's still in the realm of
just of an investigator's choice
and I think you know there we really
have to figure out how to ask
when do we think we're going to get
something interesting out of applying
this framework to a given object of
study or to a specific object of study
and when do we think we'll be doing
something sort of like
rederiving evolution
[Music]
where like it's useful to do as a formal
exercise
but to my knowledge we haven't learned
anything new about Evolution from the
free energy principle or active
inference that we didn't know before
mainly because people had already
described evolution in terms of
inference
you know prior to describing it in terms
of active inference
I I think another another thing that's
useful to think about and I've been
thinking about this a lot lately is in
terms of
what are some of the metaphors that
we're using to scaffold the scientific
questions that we're asking
um because I think one of the things
that
one of the things that's a big strength
of this paper of Eli is right is that
the title itself is actually a sequence
of two metaphors which is
interceptionist modeling allostasis as
control
so I think
there's a sense that um
if we have particular question you know
if we
set ourselves up to think what is the um
what's the sort of framework that we're
using for thinking about the questions
that are interesting or not as Eli's
saying what are the systems that are
interesting
what sort of metaphor is a Markov
blanket what sort of metaphor is active
inference what are the sort of things
that these are directing us to look at
and does thinking of control
um in the way that this paper has been
doing direct us in a different direction
to think about things in like a slightly
different way maybe
can I tag on that right away yeah can I
get your response to this Jordan so it's
the metaphor
consistently is one of the elements
baked into the metaphor non-continuity
meaning whether it would build a bridge
over it or whether we all leap across
the creek hand in hand and then the
second time we do it we all go we
because we did it twice and now we have
some no confirmation that we can do it
it's the is the consistency within the
metaphor the non-continuity I know we
perceive it sometimes as being
continuous and Progressive
but are we talking
whether we're talking Markov blanket or
whether we're talking anything that's
gap
respecting is not necessarily Gap
filling that's my question to you
Jordan what do you think I think it's I
think it's more about the Gap respecting
than the constantly searching for
something to jam and wedge in it
because that that space that that Eli
spoke to that that possibilities thing
that really matters in terms of
Staying Alive
right it's not when you're getting out
of the particulars Max ramstead says
there is no rule for that yet that's
that's what you have to self-organize so
what do you think
I don't know I don't know how to answer
that
I'm trying to familiarize feel but but
what I but I guess
um so then Jordan I think you should
prep what you're saying for a moment and
I'll give an answer to that for sure or
you just take over
so I think the thing is that at least in
our lab we are a physiologically focused
affective science lab right and so we
sort of come to active inference with
a set of systems of interest and a set
of phenomena of interest in mind already
and that doesn't necessarily
help other people pick out what they
want but it does indicate that you can
bring what you want to
I think active inference ends up being a
bit of a potluck feel at a certain point
that's a good answer yeah yep one
thought on that is the structure of a
lab with a system or a question in mind
is uh epistemic framework that allows
the investigators
to actually take on bold's new
theoretical choices
and explore different Frameworks that
are investigating a specified system of
Interest like we're studying blood
pressure regulation in the context of
professional dodgeball players or
interceptive awareness in intramural
dodgeball players
when there's already a project or a need
specified
in potentially even variability retained
setting
then the lab exists to funnel that
into
different kinds of analyzes and
scenarios that help
address that system like all of the lab
studying different human diseases
and sometimes and with challenges and
successes
making their work in the lab connect
back to the real world and being able to
take on new theoretical perspectives
some which might not initially appear to
be helpful
until years of basic research have
occurred around some molecule or Gene
family
so yeah that's very interesting what
Maxwell added and I think speaks a lot
to
many of the Notions that we've been
discussing
like pushing at not having two Realms
the metabasian with a highly rule-based
and then leaving the outer level with
where there is no strategy
we just accept the priors without having
metacognition on that level
because that's just the limits of how
far
the model was extended out
yep
um
do other review Author just want to add
anything about dodgeball
well yes yes I was going to tell I was
going to tell everyone why it was
DodgeBall so
um
essentially in basketball
you have to shoot To The Hoop so you
throw the ball goes it either goes into
the hoop or it misses if you're passing
you know the person either catches or
you missed
in DodgeBall the ball is coming at you
and so the idea here is that you're
picturing yourself trying to dodge
and this lets us sort of
merge the intuitions about predictive
processing and control where the
reference signal is to avoid contact
with the ball
so therefore the stimulus becomes both a
prediction error and an actual control
error
foreign
dodgeball with something
I mean if you walk out into the middle
of a traffic yes like
there's always some obscure possibility
of being you know hit by a rock out of
nowhere but hopefully most of the time
in life you're not actually playing
dodgeball with something well there's
always something that can disrupt you
right yeah there's always I don't know
do you have a system that can be
disrupted in many ways I'm just picking
on it because I think again it's it's
about metaphors right and I think when
you're talking about basketball
you're talking about having a goal
you're talking about having um some sort
of externally defined goal that you're
trying to perform actions to satisfy and
then you tally up the score in some way
of it right
versus in Dodgeball
you can get hit and you're out and you
know the same thing is true of your your
physiological systems can get disrupted
and you're out you're dead right
yeah but I guess my intuition is that in
DodgeBall the ball is coming for you
in a way that most of the time it isn't
physiologically no that's true metaphors
aren't perfect but I'm just saying that
yeah this physiology is not adversarial
no no
but there is yeah oh no sorry go ahead
just remind me at each sport
provides kind of a difference
metaphor none of them total or of course
exact but there's games where you're
avoiding the ball there's games where
you have to hit an inanimate object and
then it bounces off like ball ball
um there's games with implements without
implements
there's marathoning
they're sprinting there's throwing
things then there's just one two three
eleven all numbers of different players
on ice as Dean knows and each of these
settings have their interceptive
challenges and social included in that
model Dean yeah I was just going to say
the metaphor you can have you can have a
lattice of rope that makes you a bridge
and you can have a lot of rope that
makes you a fishing net one captures
one allows you to cross one is in
between one is enveloping and I think
that's why we use metaphors but at the
point that I would make is that
when you mesh something you still have
those gaps and I think it's important to
see the non-continuity in this I think
that's where the math
the theoretical the ability to bring it
down to that level if it's not if it's
not only one
if it's not received as only being one
math
if there are maths involved I think you
create the conditions around which
better understanding can move forward
now to Jordan's point it takes longer if
you don't have the proper gauge of mesh
to catch the smaller fish and that's I
think what Maxwell was speaking to it's
up to you to decide
whether you're catching Guppies or tuna
there's a there's your metaphor for the
daytime
one short thought is the a zero to one
which is a boundary we can talk about in
the future is
um when the entire or large subsets of
the active inference ontology and
frankly just the use of statistical
modeling these kinds of Transformations
are not
2022 sanesh at all inventions with
respect to control processes
um once one undertakes the statistics
toolkit
they enable new visibilities into what
was already latent every time somebody
had shown something in terms of a CDF
they didn't always show this but this is
also taking logs of variables and
interchanging CDF and PDF some of these
Atomic units already exist
and this paper does an incredible job of
putting
the setting of interception and the
function of allostasis
into
the intersecting
legacies of
control theory and cybernetic approaches
as well as more recent developing
threads many of which don't have a
formal basis initially
like ecological psychology
and affective modeling
and so bringing those two areas together
is kind of that psychologist engineer
conversation that was brought up and
that's like the dodgeball game now are
they throwing if they hit each other do
they knock each other out or are they
sending each other
you know and as we explored initially
it's not clear
and the in that uncertainty in the
beginning of the exchange it's not like
the dodgeballs are particles they're
more like waves
what will Jordan and Eli your
post paper
directions be or how long are you going
to be continuing or what directions here
Jordan I think you should tell them
about our lab meeting next week
oh yeah we're we're covering um
so I think one of the things is we've
talked about uh
controlling variables here
we were interested in um or I'm
interested at least in thinking about a
for other control perspectives there's a
perspective perceptual control theory
um to think about whether the uh
that basically the behavior is a means
of um
controlling inputs or controlling
sensory inputs to a system
but more specifically I'm interested in
um
thinking about how we can apply Control
Systems thinking to Neuroscience more
generally so I think people are very
used to taking an fmri image for example
a bold Imaging
and then treating it as an input output
system where they deliver some sort of
stimuli to the brain they'll observe
some output which will be a bold
response in some region and then they'll
interpret that as causal that they
deliver a stimuli they see an effect in
the brain and they have to they've
identified some cause effect
relationship and the problem is that
people have been doing that for 20 30
years now you have a million different
strands of these supposed cause effect
relationships and you don't have a whole
lot to structure them and a different
way to think about it is that the brain
is um
is a negative feedback controlled system
that's trying to regulate some uh
homeostatic variables within it or
allostatic when we consider them in the
context that we're doing
so if we deliver some sort of
stimulation to the brain
we're basically perturbing sensory input
to it and then we're seeing some
perceptual response or we're seeing some
restabilization within the brain to
bring it back to homeostasis within a
region
um and we're not really
getting it causal relationships we're
looking at control systems that are
being perturbed so that's coming off of
the chapter that was by Henry Yin called
the crisis in Neuroscience which there's
also really great on brain inspired
podcast episode about that too which is
worth checking out of
and Eli you have some ideas too to
follow up to think about um
control and affects right
yeah so um
us to start with that
I would sort of make a small Amendment
to the notion of a negative feedback
control system
um Jordan can you catch the podcast link
yeah sorry I could okay I know I've got
it um
and say
you know maybe we should be thinking
about nervous systems as mixed feedback
control systems
so sometimes you need to stabilize a
state of sensitivity to the environment
rather than resilience against the
environment and that would involve
positive feedback
and that's sort of where I get into
thinking about affect is that
you know if you say that there's
sort of these two modes of control
positive feedback stabilized control for
states that are very sensitive to the
environment
and then negative feedback
purely negative feedback really it's
positive feedback in the service of
negative feedback over the long run and
then purely negative feedback states
that are trying to be insensitive to the
environment and you have failure and
success
or either of them
and all of a sudden it sort of starts to
look and you can structure the feedback
loops in different ways it starts to
look
more like some of the core properties of
affect that jump out in our data
and sorry that's a very hand wavy
explanation and it's because like we
really don't have
like I don't have this in the form of
more than a few notes on my iPad
but there's should I link the other
brain inspired episode yeah yes like
that that one's good enough that I
included a quote from it in
I think in my slides from here that we
had
it's the Rudolph
yes yeah yeah controllers to engineering
what philosophy is to the humanities
wow
wow very interesting directions
Ian and Dean what are your next research
and education directions
um I'll go first I'm gonna
listen to those podcasts this is my next
steps and
I've just really enjoyed this
conversation and
um what I think
you're all all trying to achieve is
amazing stuff and it's whether it's
whether
um
studying humans is going to help us make
better AI on robotics or whether
attempting to make better you know
engineer better machines is going to
help us understand humans or whether you
know we're gonna as you said Jordan
bounce off each other and improve our
understanding both ways I think it's
um it's a good thing
foreign
thanks Ian thank you Ian thank you Eli
thank you Jordan always thank you Daniel
I I think
um
I think the last two and I want to thank
Dave Douglas although he's not on a tile
today as well because he was there for
the um dot one
it's it's really rewarding you when you
can actually have a conversation with
people like I mean normally it's throw
out the the Dodge balls and then if you
had this conversation in that in that
space
you know it would basically be yelled
out of the gym so they could get on with
the game and then there's these people
that would actually want to figure out
well what's really going on here you
know besides the person that leaves and
has to get the ice pack because they got
hit in the head or whatever and I think
the I think the idea that a bunch of
individuals can sit down and have one of
these perspective swap sessions because
they're all really good translators in
their particular area of focus
really it kind of changes the idea
around what we've been doing and we're
trying to do an active inference which
is you know create create a bigger tent
create a sense that people with
different backgrounds don't have to feel
strange because they don't well I don't
know as much about active inferences Max
Randstad so I'm going to spend ten
thousand hours to have a conversation
about this that's not what we're about
what we're trying to do is pull a bunch
of people into the room and let them
translate together swap those
perspectives actually go away as Ian
said I mean I'm going to go away now and
figure out what why really why does this
laser idea work not just sort of in a
hypothesis in my brain but really go
away and think about that for a bit and
I think if we can do that more
um and uh you know semi-formal way you
still have to cover the content and you
still need to get the contextual
background but to get to this place
where we are today Jordan to your point
it takes time but man the rewards and
the payoffs
it's just huge and again again Daniel
all the work that he puts into doing
this
it's just it's awesome so thank you
thank you yeah
this is really fun yeah great
conversation so really appreciate it
also as always
all right till the dot three anytime you
or anyone else want to continue or
present any other time always welcome so
farewell
thank you very much bye awesome thanks